<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://www.sethjhill.com/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://www.sethjhill.com/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-10-05T15:47:01-07:00</updated><id>http://www.sethjhill.com/blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Seth Hill’s blog</title><subtitle>Blog for political scientist and professor Seth Hill.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Electing the President from the House</title><link href="http://www.sethjhill.com/blog/2020/10/04/house-elected-president/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Electing the President from the House" /><published>2020-10-04T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-04T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://www.sethjhill.com/blog/2020/10/04/house-elected-president</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.sethjhill.com/blog/2020/10/04/house-elected-president/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;imperial-presidency&quot;&gt;Imperial Presidency&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been a skeptic of the Imperial Presidency argument made by Schleshinger and others. My skepticism is based on my reasoning that Congress has power to curtail most executive overreach if they so choose. Because they choose not, I have inferred they endorse, or at least are not too opposed, to the executive actions, not that the president has an imperial over the legislature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The past four years, along with a reconsideration of some actions of the Obama and Bush presidencies, has made me question my skepticism. Not because I was wrong about congressional power. Instead, it has become clear that the incentives of party politics are now such that Congress is much less inclined to use its power to check executive overreach. Members of the president’s party in Congress rarely act to curb executive action and members of the opposition party are limited in their ability to check the executive on their own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question is what to do under these circumstances. Thinkers on this topic come to opposite conclusions. Bob Bauer and Jack Goldsmith have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lawfareblog.com/lawfares-publishing-book-bob-bauer-and-jack-goldsmiths-after-trump&quot;&gt;a new book&lt;/a&gt; arguing for a platform of statutory and administrative policy reforms to rein in the executive and increase accountability of the executive to Congress. In other words, they argue the response to executive overreach is to increase congressional checks on the executive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will Howell and Terry Moe, in contrast, have &lt;a href=&quot;https://press.uchicago.edu/ucp/books/book/chicago/P/bo58173644.html&quot;&gt;a new book&lt;/a&gt; arguing for giving more power to the executive. In other words, they argue the response to executive overreach is to decrease congressional checks on the executive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both books offer proposals with the goal to increase accountability of the president and the executive branch. The Bauer Goldsmith book suggests we increase the president’s accountability to Congress. The Howell Moe book suggests we increase the president’s accountability to the electorate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neither solution, however, seems to me to get at the heart of the problem. The heart of the problem is that party politics muddy accountability of the executive for both congress and the electorate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do party politics muddy accountability? Because modern American politics is polarized, which party controls the presidency has considerable importance for national policy. Because modern American politics is highly competitive, with both sides able to imagine they can win the next election, any action to dent the standing of a copartisan president is risky. It could be the dent that hands the election to the other party. Thus, whether you are a member of Congress or a member of the electorate, taking action to hold an executive to account means taking a risk of losing the next election. Both members of Congress and voters who want to rein in an executive of their own party must trade off risks to policy representation for accountability. At this point, it seems few voters and few members of Congress are willing to make much of a trade in that direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this is the heart of the problem, how can we reform institutions to create a mechanism of accountability in a world with polarized parties where neither voters nor members of Congress want to risk harm to their policy preferences?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is an idea: The New Jersey plan (https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Jersey_Plan) presented at the constitutional convention in 1787 proposed that the executive be elected directly by the Congress. It seems to me that the House having the power to elect the president might be a path to executive accountability consistent with polarized and competitive party politics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Electing the president from the House allows for more surgical accountability with less risks to policy goals. Under this system, the majority in the House elects the president and retains the power to replace the president as needed. Crucially, the majority can replace the president with an alternative individual that not limited to the nominee of the other major party. They can elevate a member of their own party without the risks of policy loss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The system makes the president directly accountable to the House. This accountability does not depend upon statutory or administrative policy reforms as in the Bauer and Goldsmith book, which can be revised by the legislature, ignored by the executive, or struck down by the courts. This accountability does not depend on a presidential election every four years with voters’ only option to replace the malfeasant incumbent with a challenger of different policy views.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly there are other considerations with respect to such a dramatic reform and this reform would require a constitutional amendment. However, it is worth pondering whether this amendment might return the executive to its original intent, an individual empowered to execute laws by thoroughly checked by the Congress.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="institutions" /><summary type="html">Imperial Presidency</summary></entry></feed>