<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://www.sethjhill.com/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://www.sethjhill.com/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-07-05T11:30:30-07:00</updated><id>http://www.sethjhill.com/blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Seth Hill’s blog</title><subtitle>Blog for political scientist and professor Seth Hill.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Democrats need to update their coalition if they want to influence the judiciary</title><link href="http://www.sethjhill.com/blog/2022/07/05/senate-geographic-coalitions/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Democrats need to update their coalition if they want to influence the judiciary" /><published>2022-07-05T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-07-05T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://www.sethjhill.com/blog/2022/07/05/senate-geographic-coalitions</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.sethjhill.com/blog/2022/07/05/senate-geographic-coalitions/">&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court’s &lt;em&gt;Dobbs v. Jackson Women’s Health Organization&lt;/em&gt; overturning &lt;em&gt;Roe v. Wade&lt;/em&gt; is the culmination of a strategy of Senate control pursued effecitvely by Mitch McConnell and his colleagues. A natural response for opponents of Dobbs is to try to replicate this strategy with the pro-choice Democratic party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the &lt;em&gt;geographic&lt;/em&gt; distribution of their current support, however, Democrats need to update their coalition if they want to pursue a strategy of Senate control. In 2020 &lt;strong&gt;Joe Biden and and Donald Trump each won 25 states&lt;/strong&gt;. If each party wins every seat in states won by their 2020 presidential candidate, control of judicial nominations requires the tie-breaking vote of the vice president, as now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if either party coalition wants to influence judicial nominations when the other party controls the vice presidency, &lt;strong&gt;that party must win at least one Senate seat in a state won by the other’s 2020 presidential candidate.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Winning a seat in a state won by the other party’s candidate, however, appears to be harder for the Democrats given their current coalition. The figure below plots the partisan composition of each state’s Senate delegation above the corresponding Trump margin from 2020. Each state’s postal code is shaded red if currently two Republican senators, blue if currently two Democratic senators (or independents who caucus as Democrats), and purple if a mixed-party delegation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/senate-prospects.png&quot; alt=&quot;Senate seat alignment by 2020 presidential margin&quot; title=&quot;Senate seat alignment by 2020 presidential margin&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The figure shows that Joe Biden won six states with a margin of less than 5 points and nine states with a margin less than 10 points. In only two Donald Trump states was the margin less than 5 points and in only five states less than 10 points. All else equal, it is a bigger task for Democrats to win and hold seats in Trump states than for Republicans to win and hold seats in Biden states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Republicans are already more effectively threading this needle. Each party currently holds three seats in states won by the other party’s 2020 presidential candidate. Republicans hold one seat each in Maine (Biden +9), Pennsylvania (Biden +1), and Wisconsin (Biden +0.6). Democrats hold one seat each in Ohio (Trump +8), Montana (Trump +16), and West Virginia (Trump +39).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If these three Democrat seats in Trump +8, +16, and +39 states revert to Republican, the task for Democrats is daunting. To hold a majority in the Senate during a Democratic presidency, Democrats require a strategy to hold every seat in the razor-margin 2020 states of Pennsylvania, Wisconsin, Arizona (Biden +0.3), and Georgia (Biden +0.2). The next figure zooms in on the closest states, which shows that both Michigan and Nevada are also nontrivial to defend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/senate-prospects-close-states.png&quot; alt=&quot;Senate seat alignment by 2020 presidential margin, close states&quot; title=&quot;Senate seat alignment by 2020 presidential margin, close states&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But holding Biden states yields only 50 seats. To maintain a majority during a Republican vice-presidency requires winning the Maine, Pennsylvania, and Wisconsin seats AND either holding one of the Ohio, Montana, or West Virginia seats or picking up a seat in the closest Trump states, North Carolina (Trump +1), Florida (Trump +3), or Texas (Trump +6).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Republicans have a similar but, I would suggest, easier task. With the current alignment of party support, they need only pick off one seat in one of the four states Biden won by less than 2 percentage points and then recapture the Ohio, Montana, and West Virginia seats (all three up in 2024).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Democrats want future influence over the federal judiciary, the party must build an electoral coalition that can succeed in Senate races in Pennsylvania, Wisconsin, Arizona, Georgia, North Carolina, Florida, and Texas in non-wave elections. I have suggested &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.latimes.com/opinion/story/2020-02-06/health-care-swing-states-democrats-campaigns&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;elsewhere&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that one approach for developing geography-specific electoral strategies is to look to the candidates of your party who are succeeding in those geographies. What Democrats are exceeding expectations in such states today?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; language=&quot;javascript&quot;&gt;
  var sc_project=1954844; var sc_invisible=1;
  var sc_security=&quot;152490bf&quot;;
 &lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;https://www.statcounter.com/counter/counter.js&quot; async=&quot;&quot;&gt;
 &lt;/script&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="parties" /><summary type="html">The Supreme Court’s Dobbs v. Jackson Women’s Health Organization overturning Roe v. Wade is the culmination of a strategy of Senate control pursued effecitvely by Mitch McConnell and his colleagues. A natural response for opponents of Dobbs is to try to replicate this strategy with the pro-choice Democratic party.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">American endorsement of conspiracy theories is smaller than you think</title><link href="http://www.sethjhill.com/blog/2021/12/03/acquiescence-bias/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="American endorsement of conspiracy theories is smaller than you think" /><published>2021-12-03T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-12-03T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://www.sethjhill.com/blog/2021/12/03/acquiescence-bias</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.sethjhill.com/blog/2021/12/03/acquiescence-bias/">&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; language=&quot;javascript&quot;&gt;
  var sc_project=1954844; var sc_invisible=1;
  var sc_security=&quot;152490bf&quot;;
 &lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;https://www.statcounter.com/counter/counter.js&quot; async=&quot;&quot;&gt;
 &lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If news headlines are accurate, many Americans hold deeply troubling conspiratorial beliefs about political and other issues. For example, NBC News writes, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/meet-the-press/study-finds-nearly-one-five-americans-believe-qanon-conspiracy-theories-n1268722&quot;&gt;“Study finds nearly one-in-five Americans believe QAnon conspiracy theories”&lt;/a&gt; because 15 percent of respondents to a survey agreed with the statement “the government, media, and financial worlds in the U.S. are controlled by a group of Satan-worshipping pedophiles who run a global child sex trafficking operation.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.prri.org/research/qanon-conspiracy-american-politics-report/&quot;&gt;same poll&lt;/a&gt;, 29 percent of respondents completely or mostly agreed with the statement “The 2020 election was stolen from Donald Trump.” &lt;!--- Question wording =  Do you agree or disagree with each of the following? &quot;Q9a. The government, media, and financial worlds in the U.S. are controlled by a group of Satan-worshipping pedophiles who run a global child sex trafficking operation.&quot;
&quot;The 2020 election was stolen from Donald Trump.&quot; https://www.prri.org/wp-content/uploads/2021/05/Topline-IFYC-PRRI-Survey-on-Religion-and-COVID-19-Vaccine-Trust-v2_final.pdf ---&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But these conclusions might be overstated. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.margaretroberts.net&quot;&gt;Molly Roberts&lt;/a&gt; and I show in our paper &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sethjhill.com/HillRoberts_AcqBiasPoliticalBeliefs.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Acquiescence Bias Inflates Estimates of Conspiratorial Beliefs and Political Misperceptions&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that &lt;em&gt;how you ask questions&lt;/em&gt; in opinion surveys can &lt;em&gt;bias conclusions about political beliefs&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We find that &lt;em&gt;acquiescence-response bias&lt;/em&gt; – the tendency for survey respondents to endorse any assertion made in a survey question regardless of content – inflates the number of survey respondents who &lt;em&gt;agree&lt;/em&gt; with political conspiracies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is, if you ask respondents if they agree or disagree with the statement&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The 2020 election was stolen from Donald Trump&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;more will claim to agree than will disagree if you ask respondents if they agree or disagree with the statement&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The 2020 election was not stolen from Donald Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because questions about conspiracy theories are often framed similar to the first rather than the second, acquiesence bias inflates the number of survey respondents who say they agree with the statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-research&quot;&gt;The research&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We replicated work from recent published academic articles on political beliefs in the United States and China. We fielded six new surveys covering a range of topics, samples, elicitation instruments, and types of misperceptions and conspiracies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To measure acquiescence bias, we used a simple research design. For each question asking a bout a political belief on each survey, we fielded both the original version of the question and an alternative version of the same question that flips the meaning of the agreeable response so that in the alternative version acquiescence bias works in the opposite direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-findings&quot;&gt;The findings&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We found that survey respondents do not return the same rate of endorsement to the two versions of each question on the majority of questions across samples, topics, instruments, and types of belief. Acquiescence bias inflates estimates by up to 50%. We found particularly large acquiescence bias on questions about democratic norms and the transition of power following the 2020 American presidential election.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below we present Figure 1 from our paper, which compares the rate endorsing political beliefs across 55 different questions for those asked the question where agreement indicates endorsement of the conspiracy or belief (“positive-keyed” on the x-axis) to the rate endorsing for those asked the question where agreement indicates non-endorsement (“negative-keyed” on the y-axis). All but one of the points falls below the 45 degree line, which means a larger proportion of respondents endorse the conspiracy when asked the positive- than when asked the negative-keyed version. This is acquiescence bias.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/acq-bias-45.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Effect of question wording on agreement with rumors and facts&quot; title=&quot;Effect of question wording on agreement with rumors and facts&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;bias-particularly-prevalent-among-ideologues&quot;&gt;Bias particularly prevalent among ideologues&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent years, many prominent studies and news stories have reported on troubling magnitudes of conspiracy beliefs by ideological conservatives. We found that subjects who identify as very conservative exhibit larger acquiescence bias than both those who identify as very liberal and those with less ideological identification. Our results suggest that existing conclusions in part are driven by greater acquiescence bias by survey respondents with conservative leanings rather than greater endorsement of conspiracies by conservatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;methods-to-correct-for-acquiescence-bias&quot;&gt;Methods to correct for acquiescence bias&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We not only show how acquiescence bias inflates survey estimates of endorsement of conspiratorial beliefs. We also present some simple statistical fixes to correct for the bias. We show that if analysts field two versions of each question, one where the acquiescent response indicates endorsement of the conspiracy and one where the acquiescent response indicates non-endorsement of the conspiracy, combining responses from the two versions of the question can cancel out acquiescence bias. This yields an estimate closer to the likely true rate of endorsement in the population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also propose corrections for the correlation of acquiescence bias with political ideology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;be-cautious-with-dire-news-headlines&quot;&gt;Be cautious with dire news headlines&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our study does not show that conspiratorial beliefs are absent or that democracy is not in trouble. But it does show that consumers of political surveys and political news ought to be cautious about drawing conclusions from survey responses about political beliefs. And it shows that those who design surveys should account for acquiescence bias when writing questions to measure beliefs about political issues and conspiracies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="political" /><category term="beliefs" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to reduce greenhouse gas emissions, unlock $1 trillion of land, and free 1 billion days of time</title><link href="http://www.sethjhill.com/blog/2021/03/23/challenge-prize-flying-cars/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to reduce greenhouse gas emissions, unlock $1 trillion of land, and free 1 billion days of time" /><published>2021-03-23T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-03-23T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://www.sethjhill.com/blog/2021/03/23/challenge-prize-flying-cars</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.sethjhill.com/blog/2021/03/23/challenge-prize-flying-cars/">&lt;p&gt;Congress and the Biden Administration are in discussions on a multi-trillion dollar infrastructure bill. Much of that money would fund construction of roadways using concrete, steel, and asphalt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For our climate, let’s pause on this one. Let’s start by funding &lt;strong&gt;challenge prizes for the three best flying car produced in the next year&lt;/strong&gt;. Give the world twelve months and then award a first-place prize of $1 billion, a second place prize of $750 million, and a third place prize of $250 million. Have minimum parameters for the entries, something like (a) must fly 15 miles in 15 minutes, (b) vertical take off and landing, (c) electric or gasoline engine at equal or lower emissions than foor-door sedan, and (d) noise limited to some reasonable magnitue. This would be a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inducement_prize_contest&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;inducement prize contest&lt;/a&gt; in the great historical tradition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flying cars could not only decrease greenhouse gas emissions, but could save billions of hours of time commuting and free up trillions of dollars of urban land. To see how we can free up &lt;strong&gt;9 New York Cities of urban land&lt;/strong&gt; in the United States, read on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;for-the-climate&quot;&gt;For the climate&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flying cars would combat climate change. You already know that gasoline engines contribute somewhere around &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ipcc.ch/site/assets/uploads/2018/02/ipcc_wg3_ar5_chapter8.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;one quarter of global CO2 emissions&lt;/a&gt;. But production of concrete, cement, iron, and steel contribute another &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oecd.org/greengrowth/GGSD2019_IssuePaper_CementSteel.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;12-14%, and growing&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, infrastructure spending on traditional concrete and asphalt roads is a &lt;strong&gt;greenhouse gas behemoth&lt;/strong&gt;. What can we do to lessen that impact?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flying cars would need far less concrete, asphalt, and steel to support transport routes. Imagine not needing to build and maintain so many surface streets and freeways. You need a place to take off and a place to land. The sky is your roadway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/FlyingCars2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Three-dimensional commuting: Back to the Future&quot; title=&quot;Three-dimensional commuting&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flying cars also expand routes in a third dimension so that we don’t all need to cluster onto the same two-dimensional roads. This means less congestion, fewer stop signs, and fewer traffic lights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reducing congestion and stop-and-go driving through this third dimension would decrease energy use. Below is a figure of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fueleconomy.gov/feg/atv.shtml&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;energy use in gasoline vehicles&lt;/a&gt;. Because of the physics of the internal combustion engine, only 16-25% of the gasoline’s energy powers the wheels. In typical use, half of that 16-25% is used to overcome rolling resistance (friction with the roadway) and in braking (stop-and-go).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fueleconomy.gov/feg/atv.shtml&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/energy_reqs_combined_072517.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Where the Energy Goes: Gasoline Vehicles&quot; title=&quot;Where the Energy Goes: Gasoline Vehicles&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traveling in a flying car rather than via two-dimensional roadways allows avoiding congestion, stop signs, and traffic lights and could mean point-to-point transit so less total distance traveled. All these factors would notably cut energy costs in transit. Takeoff for flying vehicles is doubtless costly in energy. My hunch, though, is that this is outweighed by the energy savings of point-to-point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cutting-our-commute-and-growing-our-cities&quot;&gt;Cutting our commute and growing our cities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Benefits to flying cars extend well beyond infrastructure costs and climate change. Imagine the benefits to commute times and land use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2019, 148 million Americans commuted to work at an average &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.census.gov/content/dam/Census/library/publications/2021/acs/acs-47.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;round-trip duration of 55.2 minutes&lt;/a&gt;. That is &lt;strong&gt;221 hours of commuting per worker per year&lt;/strong&gt; or more than &lt;strong&gt;1.3 billion 24-hour days spent commuting by American workers&lt;/strong&gt;. In a single year. Imagine the time and potential unlocked by cutting this number even by 10 percent, let alone in half or more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- ![Commuting](/blog/assets/Commute.jpg &quot;Commuting&quot;){: width=&quot;500&quot;  target=&quot;_blank&quot;} --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/39932276@N00/321100379&quot; title=&quot;Traffic jam&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://live.staticflickr.com/124/321100379_0bcfc95d3c_k.jpg&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; alt=&quot;Traffic jam&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flying cars would save us space in addition to time. I estimate that &lt;strong&gt;public roadways take up 5,600 square miles – more than 6 percent – of Federal Urbanized Areas in the United States&lt;/strong&gt;. To give you a sense of scale, New York City covers 302.6 square miles. Sprawling Houston covers 669.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roadways use massive amounts of highly valuable real estate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is my calculation: In 2019, the United States had an estimated &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fhwa.dot.gov/policyinformation/statistics/2019/vmt422c.cfm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;8.8 million lane-miles&lt;/a&gt; of public roadways with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fhwa.dot.gov/policyinformation/statistics/2019/hm260.cfm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;2.8 million&lt;/a&gt; in Federal Urbanized Areas – densely settled core geographies of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.census.gov/programs-surveys/geography/guidance/geo-areas/urban-rural/2010-urban-rural.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;at least 50,000 people&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The American Road &amp;amp; Transportation Builders Association &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.artba.org/about/faq/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;estimates&lt;/a&gt; that every 1,000 lane-miles covers about two square miles of area. Combining this estimate with the DOT numbers suggests public roadways use about 5,600 square miles of Urbanized Areas. This is 6.3 percent of the Federal Urbanized Area total surface area of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www2.census.gov/geo/docs/reference/ua/ua_list_all.txt&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;88,500 square miles&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine what we could do if we reclaimed half of that land. These 2,800 square miles would be the equivalent of &lt;strong&gt;9 New York Cities&lt;/strong&gt;. And this land is some of the most valuable on earth. If urban land in America was worth &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2017-11-02/america-s-urban-land-is-worth-a-staggering-amount&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;$500,000 per acre in 2010&lt;/a&gt; and has since increased in value &lt;a href=&quot;https://fred.stlouisfed.org/graph/?g=C982&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;by 50 percent&lt;/a&gt;, these 2,800 square miles of urban roadways cover around &lt;strong&gt;$1.3 trillion&lt;/strong&gt; of land. Even with downward price pressure from increased supply, it’s hard to imagine the land would be less productive for our economy than concrete. Imagine the housing supply or greenspace that might be built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further reading&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Kindle eBook &lt;a href=&quot;https://read.amazon.com/kp/embed?asin=B07F6SD34R&amp;amp;preview=newtab&amp;amp;linkCode=kpe&amp;amp;ref_=cm_sw_r_kb_dp_B6GJFRW50VV7PBP1FVCH&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Where’s My Flying Car?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by J. Storrs Hall prompted some of these ideas. The book is fascinating if a little preachy. Hall’s history of the death of the flying car industry is devasting as to the stultifying effects of air travel regulations. For a short review of the book, check out &lt;a href=&quot;https://rootsofprogress.org/where-is-my-flying-car&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Roots of Progress&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-payoff&quot;&gt;The payoff&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$1 trillion in urban land value, another $1 trillion in avoided infrastructure costs, 1 billion work-days of commuting, and a non-trivial decrease in the transportation and construction vectors that currently generate 40% of CO2 emissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-ask&quot;&gt;The ask&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My $2 billion ask is a penance compared to multi-trillion dollar economic benefits, life satisfaction from a reduction in commute times, and reduction in greenhouse gas emissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s aim big. Combat climate change. Improve our lives. Grow our economies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Challenge prizes for flying cars, please.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; language=&quot;javascript&quot;&gt;
  var sc_project=1954844; var sc_invisible=1;
  var sc_security=&quot;152490bf&quot;;
 &lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;https://www.statcounter.com/counter/counter.js&quot; async=&quot;&quot;&gt;
 &lt;/script&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="technology" /><category term="climate-change" /><summary type="html">Congress and the Biden Administration are in discussions on a multi-trillion dollar infrastructure bill. Much of that money would fund construction of roadways using concrete, steel, and asphalt.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">To start a non-Trumpist third party, think big by going small</title><link href="http://www.sethjhill.com/blog/2021/03/05/third-party/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="To start a non-Trumpist third party, think big by going small" /><published>2021-03-05T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-03-05T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://www.sethjhill.com/blog/2021/03/05/third-party</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.sethjhill.com/blog/2021/03/05/third-party/">&lt;p&gt;With Donald Trump’s dominance of the Republican party seemingly unassailable, the conservative critics of Trumpism who opposed his election and re-election are on the hunt for a new political home. Some have argued for creating a new third party while others propose working within the Democratic coalition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why not both?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See the remainder of the piece at &lt;a href=&quot;https://thebulwark.com/to-start-a-non-trumpist-third-party-think-big-by-going-small/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Bulwark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; language=&quot;javascript&quot;&gt;
  var sc_project=1954844; var sc_invisible=1;
  var sc_security=&quot;152490bf&quot;;
 &lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;https://www.statcounter.com/counter/counter.js&quot; async=&quot;&quot;&gt;
 &lt;/script&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="elections" /><summary type="html">With Donald Trump’s dominance of the Republican party seemingly unassailable, the conservative critics of Trumpism who opposed his election and re-election are on the hunt for a new political home. Some have argued for creating a new third party while others propose working within the Democratic coalition.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What Biden should do to get things done: Delegate to the states</title><link href="http://www.sethjhill.com/blog/2021/01/28/biden-delegate/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Biden should do to get things done: Delegate to the states" /><published>2021-01-28T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-28T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://www.sethjhill.com/blog/2021/01/28/biden-delegate</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.sethjhill.com/blog/2021/01/28/biden-delegate/">&lt;p&gt;Joe Biden is president and his party narrowly controls the House and the Senate. But that doesn’t mean the Democrats will be able to push through whatever federal policies they want. To do more and effect greater change, President Biden should do two things: use his decades of legislative experience to build consensus in Congress and, when consensus isn’t possible, seek to delegate authority to cities and states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See the remainder of the piece at &lt;a href=&quot;https://thehill.com/opinion/white-house/535919-what-biden-should-do-to-get-things-done-delegate-to-the-states&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Hill&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; language=&quot;javascript&quot;&gt;
  var sc_project=1954844; var sc_invisible=1;
  var sc_security=&quot;152490bf&quot;;
 &lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;https://www.statcounter.com/counter/counter.js&quot; async=&quot;&quot;&gt;
 &lt;/script&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="institutions" /><summary type="html">Joe Biden is president and his party narrowly controls the House and the Senate. But that doesn’t mean the Democrats will be able to push through whatever federal policies they want. To do more and effect greater change, President Biden should do two things: use his decades of legislative experience to build consensus in Congress and, when consensus isn’t possible, seek to delegate authority to cities and states.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sidestepping primary reform and the consequences of partisan primaries</title><link href="http://www.sethjhill.com/blog/2020/10/28/sidestepping-reform/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sidestepping primary reform and the consequences of partisan primaries" /><published>2020-10-28T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-28T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://www.sethjhill.com/blog/2020/10/28/sidestepping-reform</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.sethjhill.com/blog/2020/10/28/sidestepping-reform/">&lt;p&gt;Many believe primary elections distort representation in American legislatures because unrepresentative actors nominate extremist candidates. Advocates have reformed primaries to make it easier for more citizens to participate and more difficult for parties to control the process. They have hoped this will improve representation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Empirical evidence, however, is quite variable as to the effects of reform. Some research finds effects of reform while others fail to detect much consequence. Why do we have such a hard time nailing down the effects of primary elections?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1017/psrm.2020.42&quot;&gt;“Sidestepping Primary Reform: Political Action in Response to Institutional Change”&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Political Science Research and Methods&lt;/em&gt;), I argue that consequences of primary reform are sometimes mitigated by political actors who circumvent reform via other pathways of influence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because actors can sidestep reform, the total effect of changes to primary institutions is more than the direct effect of reform. Reforms have multiple and varied consequences on the choices of political actors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s my DAG of what I think is going on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/sidestepping-dag.png&quot; alt=&quot;Directed Acyclical Graph: Causal pathways of primary elections&quot; title=&quot;Causal pathways of primary elections&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paper presents difference-in-differences analysis of primary rule changes in the American states from 1992 to 2014. I consider multiple outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I show that more open rules and implementation of nonpartisan primaries increase turnout in primary elections on order of 1.5 to 6 points. As reformers argued, more open rules increase rates of participation in nomination contests.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I show reforms also increase campaign contributions from individuals to political candidates. I estimate increases on the order of 9 to 21 percent in response to reform.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reforms do not, however, appear to have increased competition at primary elections. I find no effect on winning primary vote margin, number of contested primaries, or number of candidates in the contests. This suggests the increases in contributions are not because of more candidates or more competition.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These findings suggest actors substitute action across avenues of political influence to limit effects of institutional reform. Those individuals who are aggrieved by the direct consequences of reform take countervailing action. Countervailing actions complicate the total effect of reform, which is why political science analysis of primary elections comes to varying conclusions depending upon setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; language=&quot;javascript&quot;&gt;
  var sc_project=1954844; var sc_invisible=1;
  var sc_security=&quot;152490bf&quot;;
 &lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;https://www.statcounter.com/counter/counter.js&quot; async=&quot;&quot;&gt;
 &lt;/script&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="institutions" /><summary type="html">Many believe primary elections distort representation in American legislatures because unrepresentative actors nominate extremist candidates. Advocates have reformed primaries to make it easier for more citizens to participate and more difficult for parties to control the process. They have hoped this will improve representation.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Fair and Legitimizing Reform of the Supreme Court</title><link href="http://www.sethjhill.com/blog/2020/10/22/supreme-court-reform/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Fair and Legitimizing Reform of the Supreme Court" /><published>2020-10-22T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-22T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://www.sethjhill.com/blog/2020/10/22/supreme-court-reform</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.sethjhill.com/blog/2020/10/22/supreme-court-reform/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: I had planned to save this post until after the election because only one of the two candidates seem likely to have interest in reform to the judiciary. But with Biden’s proposal for a commission, I decided to post, even though it is putting the horse before the cart.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Biden campaign announced that if elected a President Biden would appoint a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnn.com/2020/10/22/politics/biden-supreme-court/index.html&quot;&gt;bipartisan commission on reform to the judiciary&lt;/a&gt;. This follows pressure from some on the left to pack the Supreme Court if they gain control of the presidency and Senate following the November 2020 election.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interest in packing follows a longer term trend of &lt;strong&gt;the politicization of judicial nominations&lt;/strong&gt;. In my view, this politicization follows from the increasing gridlock in congressional policy-making, which raises the policy stakes of judicial decisions. When Congress takes less legislative action, policy change more often occurs through judicial decisions (or executive action, which is then subject to judicial contest).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If the Democrats were to simply expand the size of the court with new lifetime appointments, it would only exacerbate politicization&lt;/strong&gt;. Instead, We should work towards a reform that is both fair and increases the legitimiacy and effectiveness of the federal judiciary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My proposal follows from a goal of &lt;strong&gt;lessening the stakes of each individual appointment&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;increasing the legitimacy of judicial decisions&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;proposal&quot;&gt;Proposal&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposal is to expand the size of the Supreme Court to twelve justices but limit the terms of each.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Each justice would be appointed for a twelve-year term with one seat expiring each year&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each seat would belong to one of the twelve judicial circuits in the United States. When a seat opens, the current president must nominate a current judge from the appellate bench of the circuit of that seat. If confirmed by the Senate, that judge would begin the twelve-year term in that circuit’s Supreme Court seat. At the end of the term, that judge would automatically return to their appellate position with lifetime appointment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This reform is packing but, in my view, packing with fairness. It is not the Senate majority simply grabbing a majority on the Court. Instead, the reform creates an even balance in the court’s current composition and sets up an institution that promotes balance and temperance moving forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This reform would remain consistent with lifetime appointment of federal judges. Judges gain lifetime appointment to the appellate court rather than the Supreme Court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;benefits&quot;&gt;Benefits&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This reform would &lt;strong&gt;lower the stakes of Supreme Court nominations&lt;/strong&gt;. Each confirmation is for twelve years rather than for life. Annual turnover is certain. Every elected president is guaranteed a fixed number of appointments, one for each year in office. Every confirmation is one of twelve justices rather than one of nine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because appointments are not lifetime terms, &lt;strong&gt;nominee age need not be a factor&lt;/strong&gt;. We might focus more exclusively on which nominee would be the best justice. Every nominee has recorded decisions from the appellate court to evaluate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reforming the Supreme Court to an even number of judges would make &lt;strong&gt;single-vote, party-line decisions less common&lt;/strong&gt;. Additions to Supreme Court precedent would, in general, require greater agreement. Decisions that result in ties would revert to the lower court ruling, allowing for more variation in precedent around the country consistent with federalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we all know that Supreme Court decisions require more agreement, &lt;strong&gt;decisions have more legitimacy&lt;/strong&gt;. Americans detest monarch-like lawmakers. Currently five unelected lawyers wield ultimate power through judicial review. An even, twelve-justice court disperses the power of judicial review to more individuals and, with ties more likely, disperses power back to lower courts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Current members of the federal bench benefit from increasing legitimacy&lt;/strong&gt;. Deleveraging the stakes of any individual appointment helps make nominations more about process, rule of law, and legal acumen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reform might encourage greater &lt;strong&gt;stability in the law&lt;/strong&gt;. Rotating justices know that one day they will be bound by their own Supreme Court decisions when returned to the appellate bench. This might encourage opinions with clearer guidance to lower courts, or even more deference to lower court decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A larger Supreme Court panel could also deal with &lt;strong&gt;a larger case load&lt;/strong&gt;. They could operate like the appellage circuits with three-judge panels hearing more cases to make initial decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number twelve is only one option that follows from the number of judicial circuits. One drawback is that a president who wins two terms to office would nominate eight of twelve justices by the end of their term in office. This might be more political than desirable. It might be reasonable to consider a sixteen-member court with sixteen-year terms, so that no single president could be responsible for more than half of the court’s composition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; language=&quot;javascript&quot;&gt;
  var sc_project=1954844; var sc_invisible=1;
  var sc_security=&quot;152490bf&quot;;
 &lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;https://www.statcounter.com/counter/counter.js&quot; async=&quot;&quot;&gt;
 &lt;/script&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="institutions" /><summary type="html">Note: I had planned to save this post until after the election because only one of the two candidates seem likely to have interest in reform to the judiciary. But with Biden’s proposal for a commission, I decided to post, even though it is putting the horse before the cart.</summary></entry></feed>